Heath O'Brien, PhD

Bioinformatician

November 2019

10 Marmaduke Street, Bristol BS3 4SQ, United Kingdom

+44 (0) 7711 045747

hobrien.github.io

heath.obrien@gmail.com

heath obrien

hobrien

Publications

heath-o-brien-198145b2

About me ——

I have 20 years of experience analyzing genetic data, both in academia and the private sector. I've worked on functional genomics, high-throughput sequencing and genotyping data from plants, fungi, bacteria and humans. I enjoy working on interdisciplinary projects and leading teams with diverse skill sets. I also have strong communication skills, having co-authored over 25 publications and presented my research at conferences in 7 countries.

Skills —

Functional genomics

Quantitative genetics

Microbiology

Data visualisation

Scientific communication

Project management

 \mathbf{R}

Python

BASH

AWS

SQL

Work History

2018-Present Lead Bioinformatician

Living DNA

- Leading a team of 6 bioinformaticians and data scientists developing methods to derive ancestry and health insights from direct-to-consumer genetics
- Managing partnerships with data suppliers, academic scientists and business incubators
- Working to secure external funding to develop novel genomic prediction approaches
- Collaboration with the engineering team to deploy processing pipelines at scale and to improve all steps of sample processing and data delivery

2016-2018 Research Associate Cardiff, UK

Frome, UK

MRC Centre for Neuropsychiatric Genetics and Genomics

- Differential gene expression and eQTL analyses on human brain samples
- Integration of functional genomics data with largescale population genomics datasets for schizophrenia and other neurophychiatric disorders
- Organization of training seminars on data science (Rstudio, MySQL), version control (Git), and pipeline development (Snakemake, Bash)
- Deployment of results on the web using R-Shiny

2013-2016 Bioinformatician

Bristol, UK

University of Bristol

- Comparative transcriptomics to determine the genetic basis of cell wall patterning responsible for colour-production in plant leaves
- Electron microscopy of light scattering nanostructures in plants and algae
- Acting group leader during nine-month family leave cover (overseeing a team of three staff and two students, managing procurement)

2008-2013 Postdoctoral Fellow

Toronto, ON, Canada

University of Toronto

- De novo assembly and comparative analyses of bacterial genomes
- Cloning of virulence factors and characterization using in-planta infection assays
- Supervision of undergraduate students

2006-2008 Lab Administrator Durham, NC, USA

Duke University

- Oversight of teaching labs for General and Advanced Microbiology
- Managed one lab technician and eight teaching assistants

Education

2000-2006 PhD, Molecular systematics of cyanobacteria Durham, NC, USA

Duke University

1994-1999 Bachelors degree, Plant Science Edmonton, AB, Canada

University of Alberta

Training

Advanced Python for Biologists, PR Statistics, February, 2017.

Advancing in R, PR Statistics, April, 2015.

Genetic Data Analysis, Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics, June, 2003.

References

Available on request.